Finding Aid for Labor Party of Washtenaw County Records, 1995-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Labor Party of Washtenaw County records 1995-1999
Labor Party of Washtenaw County
0.5 linear ft.
Administrative records include bylaws, correspondence, meeting minutes, and newsletters. Topical files concern various political groups and issues such as the Detroit newspaper strike, the appearance of the Ku Klux Klan in Ann Arbor in 1996, and other labor matters.
0166 Bt 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated to the library by Michelle J. Kinnucan (donor no. 9056 ) in January 2001.
The record group is open for research.
The Labor Party of Washtenaw County was formed in 1994 and then incorporated as a non-profit organization in 1996. The organization was known as Labor Party Advocates of Ann Arbor and Ypsilanti until 1996. Its main goal was to help build local support for the national Labor Party, a political party which grew out of the national Labor Party Advocates organization in 1996. The Labor Party maintained that concessions to corporations by the two major American political parties had led to widening income and wealth disparities in the United States. The party opposed corporate influence on elections and government, and supported the right to a living wage, quality and affordable health care, quality public education, and the protection of the environment.
The local chapter of the Labor Party, particularly chairperson Michelle Kinnucan, was involved in a wide range of state and local issues, including the Detroit Newspaper strike in the late 1990s, and response to a Ku Klux Klan rally in Ann Arbor in 1996. The party, or Kinnucan herself, was also involved with organizations such as the Washtenaw Coalition for a Living Wage, and Citizens for Quality Health Care, which opposed cost cutting measures at the University of Michigan Medical Center in 1997.
The Labor Party of Washtenaw County has been defunct since 1999.
The collection contains administrative records of the Labor Party of Washtenaw County, including by-laws, correspondence, meeting minutes, and newsletters, as well as material, collected by party chairperson Michelle Kinnucan, related to issues such as the Detroit newspaper strike, living wage campaign, health care, and the environment.
The collection has been divided into three series. Administrative Records, Topical Files, and Videocassettes.
Subjects:
Labor Party of Washtenaw County.; Detroit (Mich.); Ku Klux Klan (1915- ); Labor Party Advocates (U.S.); Strikes and lockouts--Newspapers--Michigan.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Working class--Michigan--Washtenaw County.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Labor Party of Washtenaw County.; Strikes--Michigan--Detroit.; Newspaper industry--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative Records series contains material generated by the Washtenaw County chapter of the Labor Party, and documents both the local activities of the chapter and the national issues the Labor Party sought to address. The correspondence and minutes are the largest and most significant of the administrative material.
  - Bylaws and Resolutions, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents, 1996-1999 (Box 1)
  - Presentations and Press Releases, 1996-1997 and undated (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1995-1998 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1996-1998 (Box 1)
  - National Labor Party Material, 1996 (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series contains documents related to various political groups or issues in Michigan. Some of the material, such as the Detroit newspaper strike material, documents the involvement of the Labor Party in these issues. Other files, however, such as the Habitat for Humanity material, contain few references to the Labor Party itself, and appear to be only marginally related to the organization.
  - Citizens for Quality Health Care, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Newspaper Strike (includes photographs), 1997 (Box 1)
  - Environment, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Habitat for Humanity, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Ku Klux Klan rally, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Labor Party Lesbian, Gay, Bi, Transgender Caucus, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw Coalition for a Living Wage, 1998 and undated (Box 1)
- Videotapes
  The Videocassettes series includes video segments on two cassettes, documenting the Detroit Newspaper strike in the late 1990s. One of the videocassettes also includes a segment on Chiapas, Mexico, and another entitled "People's State," concerns living conditions and state support for unemployed or low income people living in Michigan.
  - "Stoppin' the Press: Detroit Newspaper Workers Fight to Hold the Line," 1997? (Box 1)
  - "De-Scab Detroit," (video segment on Detroit newspaper workers strike and protest), 1997? (Box 1)